Guide to the Ethan Mordden Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ethan Mordden papers
1968-1991
YCAL MSS 655
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.92
(7 boxes)
Collection contains correspondence, writings, and other papers documenting the life and professional activities of author Ethan Mordden from the late 1960s to 1991. Correspondence, dating from the mid 1980s and early 1990s, contains letters from writers, actors, musicians and composers, publishers, and others, including Walta Borawski, Frank Ferko, Philip Gambone, Boze Hadleigh, Ron Hussman, Joey Manley, Kit Reed, and St. Martin's Press. Writings in the collection consist of notes and drafts for two novels, a book of film criticism entitled Medium Cool: The Movies of the 1960s (1990), and shorter works, including plays, stories, and essays. The novels "Welcome Home, Adam" (1970) and "The Friends of Lady Butch" (circa 1973-1975) are identified as Mordden's unpublished first novel and an unfinished Hollywood novel respectively. Other papers include a small amount of printed and Yale University course material.
Mordden, Ethan, 1947-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ethan Mordden, 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 7: Restricted until 2055. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Ethan Mordden (1947-)
Ethan Mordden, born January 27, 1947, is an American cultural critic and novelist. He was educated in Quaker schools, including the Friends Academy in Locust Valley, New York, and at the University of Pennsylvania (1969). He worked as a musical director and coach in New York (1971-1974), as an assistant editor of Opera News (1974-1976), and a visiting fellow at Yale University (1980). He has been a regular contributor to The New Yorker, the New York Times, and Christopher Street, among other publications. In addition to books on music, theater, and film, he publishes fiction on gay life, especially in the "Buddies" cycle, including I've a Feeling We're Not in Kansas Anymore: Tales from Gay Manhattan (1985), Buddies (1986), and Everybody Loves You: Further Adventures in Gay Manhattan (1988).
Biographical information taken from "Ethan Mordden." Baker's Biographical Dictionary of Musicians. New York: Schirmer, 2001. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 25 Oct. 2012.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and other papers documenting the life and professional activities of author Ethan Mordden from the late 1960s to 1991. Correspondence, dating from the mid 1980s and early 1990s, contains letters from writers, actors, musicians and composers, publishers, and others, including Walta Borawski, Frank Ferko, Philip Gambone, Boze Hadleigh, Ron Hussman, Joey Manley, Kit Reed, and St. Martin's Press. Writings in the collection consist of notes and drafts two for novels, a book of film criticism entitled Medium Cool: The Movies of the 1960s (1990), and shorter works, including plays, stories, and essays. The novels, "Welcome Home, Adam" (1970) and "The Friends of Lady Butch" (circa 1973-1975), are identified as Mordden's unpublished first novel and an unfinished Hollywood novel respectively. Other papers include a small amount of printed and Yale University course material.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1983-1991. II. Writings, 1970-1991. III. Other Papers, 1968-1981.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Borawski, Walta; Ferko, Frank, 1950-; Gambone, Philip; Hadleigh, Boze, 1954-; Manley, Joey; Mordden, Ethan, 1947-; Reed, Kit, 1932-2017; St. Martin's Press; Yale University
- Correspondence, 1983-1991; Series I; 2.5; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - "A" general, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes letters from Robert H. Albach, Edward Albee and Algonquin Books
  - "B" general, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - Bach, Steven, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Borawski, Walta, 1985-1991 (Box 1)
  - Butters, Ron, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - "C" general, 1983-1991 (Box 1)
  - Caswell, Judy, 1985-1991 (Box 1)
    Includes letters from Leith Chu and Jon Alan Conrad
  - "D" general, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
    Includes letters from Benjamin Donovan and John T. Dreyer
  - "E" general, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - "F" general, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Feinberg, David, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Ferko, Frank, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - "G" general, 1984-1990 (Box 1)
  - Gamble, Jeff, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Gambone, Philip, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - Garber, Eric, 1984-1986; 3 (Box 1)
  - Garman, Jack, 1987 (Box 1)
  - "H" general, 1984-1990 (Box 2)
  - Hadleigh, Boze, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Haley, Zak, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Hansen, James Hans, 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - Heinberg, Allan, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    Includes letters from Charles Hix and Michael J. Hodgson
  - Husmann, Ron, 1987 (Box 2)
  - "I" general, 1986-1990 (Box 2)
    Includes letters from Howard Israel
  - "J" general, 1985, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Jacobsson, Lars, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - James White Review, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Jones, Robert L., 1986-1989 (Box 2)
  - "K" general, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
  - Kempkes, John, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Kramer, Richard, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - "L" general, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
  - "M" general, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
  - McCain, David W., 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    Includes letters from David McClow and Robert C. Maggio
  - Manley, Joey, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Marshall, Jerry L., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Morrison, Tom, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - "N" general, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
    Includes letters from Robert H. Nielsen
  - "O" general, 1984-1990 (Box 2)
  - "P" general, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
  - Peavy, Angier, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    Includes letters from Eric G. Pindar and Steve Pollard
  - Quealy, Robert, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - "R" general, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
  - Reed, Kit, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
  - Ruman, Rick, 1985-1989 (Box 2)
  - "S" general, 1985-1991 (Box 3)
  - St. Martin's Press, 1985-1990 (Box 3)
    Includes letters by Robert Schoenberg and Jeff Selby
  - Smith, Jeffrey, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    Includes letters by Stephen Sondheim and Lynne Stuart
  - "T" general, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
  - Utas, Rikk D., 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - "V" general, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    Includes letters from James A. Van Sant
  - "W" general, 1983-1989 (Box 3)
  - "Y" general, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Unidentified, 1984-1991 (Box 3)
- Writings, 1968-1991; Series II; 2; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - Amateur Theatricals: typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 4)
  - The Beating Up of Timothy Hawkins: typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4)
  - Buddies: invitation, 1986 (Box 4)
  - The Case of the Unemployed Man: typescript carbon, corrected, [circa 1973] (Box 4)
  - A Critic at Large: autograph manuscript, typescript, proof, and printed version, 1990 (Box 4)
  - The Day After the Funeral: typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4)
  - Dragonflies are Friends of Lady Butch: autograph manuscript, undated (Box 4)
  - Early Plays, 1968-[circa 1972]; 6 (Box 4)
    Includes: Abra Cadaver, Carnivale, The Cast Against Type, Dance of Death in the Dark Hall of the Castle, Exit Pursued by a Bear, and Maximum Leader
  - Fathers and Sons: autograph manuscript and typescript, 1991 (Box 4)
  - The Friends of Lady Butch: autograph manuscript and typescript, 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - [The Ghost of Champ McQuest]: autograph manuscript, undated (Box 4)
  - Grand Hotel: notes, autograph manuscript and typescript, 1990 (Box 4)
  - The Hollywood Studio: notes, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 4)
  - How to Subvert: notes, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 4)
  - The Hunting of the Snark: autograph manuscript, undated (Box 4)
  - Look Who's Talking: typescript and typescript carbon, 1989-1990; 2 (Box 4)
  - M. J. Verlaine's book and some of the Hollywood Studios: autograph manuscript, undated (Box 4)
  - Medium Cool: notes and outline, autograph manuscript, and Chapters 1-9, setting typescript, 1990, undated; 6 (Box 5)
  - The Party of the Elite: typescript carbon, undated (Box 5)
  - The Roslyn Town Musicians: typescript carbon, undated (Box 5)
  - The Sleuth: typescript carbon, undated (Box 5)
  - The Telling Tales: autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 5)
  - The Theatre of Rodgers and Hammerstein: notebook, autograph manuscript and typescript, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - "Title TK": working proof, corrected, 1988 (Box 5)
  - [Tramps for Easter?]: autograph manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 5)
  - Welcome Home, Adam: typescript, corrected, undated (Box 5)
  - White Heat: typescript carbon, undated (Box 5)
  - Wicked Mantis is Coming for Grandma: typescript carbon, 1989 (Box 5)
  - The Writer's Strategy: autograph manuscript and typescript, [circa 1984] (Box 5)
    Includes printed material
  - Untitled notes and notebooks, undated; 3 (Box 5)
- Other Papers, 1968-1981; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type or heading.
  - Comic books, edited by Ethan Mordden, 1971-1972; 2 (Box 5)
  - Opera After Wagner: Toward an Aesthetic for Twentieth Century Art: seminar material, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Pennsylvania Review, 1968-1969 (Box 6)
- Restricted Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  - Restricted Papers (Box 7)